British Legal Records Collection, 1801-1914
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
British Legal Records Collection
Thomas Balch Library
M 110
.5 cubic feet.
British Legal Records Collection consists of seventeen documents written on parchment paper ranging in date from 1801 to 1914. These items were purchased by the donor as a mixed lot at auction, and are unrelated. Many refer to leases for a "messuage" - a dwelling house with outbuildings and land assigned to its use. The documents were registered at the Middlesex Deeds Registry and the London Land Registry.
Raymond Ruff, Lansdowne, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Raymond Ruff, Lansdowne, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2013.0144
Historical Information
A customary format for written record of property transactions developed in medieval England and became formally standardized by the 17th century. First written in Latin, all deeds after 1733 were composed in English. Each conveyance included an abstract, title deeds, supplementary documents providing proof, such as wills, certificates marriage settlements, contracts, auctioneer's papers, or other evidence. After 1840, a plan of the property was also included. Many deeds include seals, varying from elaborate pendant seals encased in a box, known as a skippet, to simple wafer seals. The absence of seals on a document may indicate that it was never executed, however, many seals have been lost or removed over time. A herring-bone pattern of cuts across a document indicates that it has been canceled, and is no longer valid. Stamps also appear on some deeds. The practice of using stamps as a form of regulating tax was first introduced in 1694. During the 18th and first third of the 19th century, stamp taxes were administered by the Board of Stamps, which became the Board of Stamps and Taxes and then the Board of Inland Revenue.
Following an act of Parliament in 1925, only thirty years of previous documentation was required to prove title to a property, and subsequently, many older documents were not retained.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of seventeen documents written on parchment paper ranging in date from 1801 to 1914. These items were purchased by the donor as a mixed lot at auction, and are unrelated. Many refer to leases for a "messuage" - a dwelling house with outbuildings and land assigned to its use. The documents were registered at the Middlesex Deeds Registry and the London Land Registry.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Alcock, N. W. 2001. Old Title Deeds: a Guide for Local and Family Historians. Chichester: Phillimore.
Clarke, Alison. Property Law: Commentary and Materials. 2005.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
    - Lease for a Year from Mr. James Waller and Others to Mr. Thomas Orchard, December 7, 1801
    - Conveyance of an Estate at Yatton in the County of Somerset from the Right Honorable John Earl Poulett and John Viscount Hinton and their Trustees to Mr. Robert Gregory, October 11, 1816
    - Settlement on the Marriage of William John Agg, Esq. with Miss Mary Morland, December 24, 1829
    - Conveyance of Two Sixths Parts of "Crosses" Estate at Rivington in the County of Lancaster from Mr. James Ashworth and Another to Mr. Thomas Anderton, December 15, 1848
    - Lease of House and Premises No. 3 Harwich Place, Peckham, Rye Common, Surrey from Mr. James Pett to Mr. William Tagg,February 24, 1854
    - Transfer of a Mortgage for Securing Payment of the Sum of 1750 British Pounds and Interest thereon from Mr. Edward Gosnell to Mr. Edward Abraham Roumieu, September 16, 1861
    - Lease of a Messuage and Premises No. 9 Wellbeck Street from the Trustees of the Will of the Most Noble William Henry Cavendish Scott Duke of Portland to Christopher Eales, Esq., August 26, 1886
    - Lease of Sutton Lodge, Turnham Green, Middlesex from George Spencer Ridgway, Esq. to Thomas Lambert, Esq., February 8, 1869
    - Lease of Premises Situate and Being in Docuras Building King Henrys Walk, Balls Pond Road from Thomas Docura, Esq. to Messrs. Jenkinson and Doubleday, September 1, 1880
    - Assignment of a Leasehold Messuage and Premises No. 112 Harley Street, Saint Marylebone in the County of Middlesex from Isaac Braithwaite, Esq. and Others to Henry Ruscoe, Esq., January 6, 1883
    - Lease of a Messuage and Premises No. 15 Upper Marlyebone Street from the Right Honorable Thomas Evelyn Baron Howard de Walden and Seaford to Mr. Richard Powell, November 11, 1904
    - Lease of a Messuage and Premises No. 20 Castle Street East from the Right Honorable Thomas Evelyn Baron Howard de Walden and Seaford to Mr. George Paxton, April 14, 1904
    - Lease of a Messuage and Premises No. 250 in Oxford Street and Known as "The Scotch Stores" from the Right Honorable Thomas Evelyn Baron Howard de Walden and Seaford to Mr. Henry Finch,May 2, 1907
    - Surrender of No. 23 Princes Street from Mr. W. A. Poole to the Right Honorable Thomas Evelyn Baron Howard de Walden and Seaford,August 11, 1909
    - Surrender of the Leasehold Premises No. 72 Harley Street from Herbert Tilley Esq. MD and the Right Honorable Thomas Evelyn Baron Howard de Walden and Seaford,April 27, 1910
    - Surrender of the Leasehold Premises No. 28 Devonshire Place from A. H. Evans, Esq. to the Right Honorable Thomas Evelyn Baron Howard de Walden and Seaford,October 1, 1914